Guide to the University Committee on Long Range Planning Records, 1958 - 1962
Duke University. University Archives
University Committee on Long Range Planning records 1958 - 1962
Duke University. University Committee on Long-Range Planning.
4.5 linear feet Extent: 4500 Items
Duke University. University Archives
The University Committee on Long Range Planning, formed in 1958, was set up to give administrative consideration to matters of educational programming and policy at Duke University. The Committee's first chairman was Paul M. Gross. Its name changed to the University Planning Committee in 1962. The collection includes correspondence, memoranda, reports, minutes, clippings, pamphlets, charts, projections, and books. It consists of records relating to the academic, faculty, and institutional development of the university. Major subjects include university planning administration, student life, institutional development, enrollment, admissions, and academic life. English.
UA.03.02.0016
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
No restrictions.
Provenance
The University Committee on Long Range Planning Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1974 (A74-36), 1982 (A82-127), and 1993 (A93-96). These transfers consist of a combination of accession A72-77, which was extracted from the files of Presidents Harts and Eden on the subject of Long Range Planning, and accession A62-163, from the files of Alan K. Manchester, Dean of Trinity College, and accession A93-96, from Professor Frank DeVyver's papers.
Historical Note
The University Committee on Long Range Planning was formed in 1958 under President A. Hollis Edens. The function according to a letter approving the committee was to give appropriate consideration to matters of educational programming and policy where institutional planning and advancement are concerned. The Committee at first dealt with issues dealing with academic life, faculty development, and the development of the quality of students and intellectual life through admissions and enrollment. During the Committee's initial academic year it authorized eleven subcommittees which dealt with the Graduate School, Social Sciences, Duke Press, Research Libraries, Science and Mathematics, Religion, Undergraduate Colleges, the University Arts Center, the Institute of Contemporary Literature, Foreign Student Programs, and the Humanities. The committee issued its first report, Planning and Development at Duke University, in June of 1959.
The Committee's first chairman was Paul M. Gross, the Vice President for Education and Dean of the University. However, on March 23, 1960 in the wake of an administrative crisis known as the Gross-Edens Affair the Board of Trustees stripped Dr. Gross of his committee chairmanship and other administrative posts. Vice-Chairman Marcus Hobbs was named to succeed him, but Hobbs tendered his resignation on March 28, 1960. Hobbs was in turn succeeded by Joseph E. Markee, another member of the committee. These events brought the future of the planning process into question. The committee informed the University's faculty and staff that it was in complete and total disagreement with the action taken by the Board of Trustees at its meeting on March 23, 1960 in removing Dr. Paul M. Gross as a member and the Chairman of the Long Range Planning Committee. In its second Progress Report, (May, 1960) the committee stated that they felt it best to suspend activities until such time as it receive[d] from the Board of Trustees and from the President of the University a satisfactory expression of their approval of the planning operation as it has been carried on (page 73). If approval was given, the committee recommended that the University extend the committee's charge until June 1961 and provide a budget to fund it through that period.
This was done; the committee's third progress report, Duke University in the Decade Ahead, was issued in June 1961. It dealt with enrollment projections, personnel and facility requirements, and financial projections. The committee concluded that systematic planning was essential and that its function should be institutionalized so as to achieve continuity and wide participation throughout the University (pages 53-54). In 1962, the University Committee on Long Range Planning was reconstituted as the University Planning Committee and assumed a stronger role in the University.
Collection Overview
The collection consists of records relating to the Committee on Long Range Planning's involvement with academic, faculty, and institutional development of the University. Correspondence, memoranda, reports, hand-written and typed minutes, clippings, pamphlets, charts, projections, books, comprise this collection. Materials range in date from 1958-1962. Although the majority of the materials were created by the Committee, some reference materials from other sources were collected by the Committee in relation to its work, including letters, reports, booklets and pamphlets about other schools and programs.
Major subjects include University and planning administration, student life (dormitories, athletics, and extracurricular activities), institutional development (philosophical beginnings and practical implementations), enrollment and admission (test data, alumni involvement, prediction equations and geographical distribution) and academic/intellectual life (graduate and undergraduate schools and departments, curriculum information and planning and faculty development).
This collection is divided into six (6) series: Minutes and Agendas, 1958-1962; Meeting Files, 1959-1961; Correspondence, 1958-1962; Reports and Recommendations, 1958-1962; and Reference Materials, 1958-1962; and Subcommittees and Committees, 1958-1962.
The Minutes and Agendas [1958-1962] series includes minutes, agendas, and summaries, and it chronicles the development of planning at the University. Meeting Files [1959-1961] is arranged chronologically and includes memos, letters, reports, booklets, bulletins, news clippings, and statistical information specifically discussed at meetings of the Committee. The materials in the meeting files, in some cases, can be matched against the materials delineated in the Committee minutes. The Committee met almost weekly during the academic year, from 1958-1962.
The Correspondence [1958-1962] represents the wide range of issues faced by the Committee. Primary correspondents consist of the President of the University, the Provost, faculty and staff members of the University, and expert professors and professionals from other universities; these include R. Taylor Cole, Marcus E. Hobbs, Paul M. Gross, A. Hollis Edens, Daryl J. Hart, Richard L. Predmore, Frank DeVyver, and Alan K. Manchester.
The Reports and Recommendations [1958-1962] series is arranged alphabetically. It includes reports and recommendations from academic and non-academic departments, graduate and professional schools, visiting experts on academic programs and departments, and University faculty and staff. Reference Materials [1958-1962] are arranged alphabetically. These folders contain reports, charts, pamphlets, and statistics collected by the Committee for use during its work.
The Subcommittees and Committees [1958-1962] series is arranged topically. The Long Range Planning Committee had a number of subcommittees, but this series includes reports, recommendations, correspondence and records of a few of these committees: the Committee on the Undergraduate Colleges, 1959-1960; the Committee on Faculty and Staff Improvement, 1960-1961; and the Committee on Professional and Graduate School, 1958-1962.
Subject Headings
Duke University -- Administration; Duke University -- Admission; Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University -- History -- 20th century; Duke University -- Planning; Duke University -- Students; Duke University. University Committee on Long-Range Planning; Campus planning; Education, Higher -- Aims and objectives; Gross, Paul Magnus, 1895-1986; Universities and colleges -- Administration; Universities and colleges -- Planning
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Minutes and Agendas, 1958-1962 (Box 1)
  Includes minutes, agendas, and running summaries. This series chronicles the development of planning at the University.
  - Minutes, 1958-1962 (Box 1)
    Minutes for January-May 1960 are missing, but running summaries are available for these meetings.
  - Agendas, 1960-1962 (Box 1)
  - Running Summaries, 1958-1962 (Box 1)
    Includes transcripts of all official meetings, prepared by the Executive Secretary of the Committee.
- Meeting Files, 1959-1961 (Box 1)
  These files include memos, letters, reports, booklets, bulletins, news clippings, and statistical information specifically discussed at meetings of the Committee. The materials in the meeting files, in some cases, correspond to the Committee minutes. The Committee met almost weekly during the academic year, from 1958-1962.
- Correspondence, 1958-1962 (Box 1)
  Correspondents include R. Taylor Cole, Marcus E. Hobbs, Paul M. Gross, A. Hollis Edens, Daryl J. Hart, Richard L. Predmore, Frank DeVyver, and Alan K. Manchester.
- Reports and Recommendations, 1958-1962 (Box 2)
  - Academic Departments, 1958-1962 (Box 2)
  - Non-Academic Departments, 1958-1962 (Box 2)
  - Faculty, 1958-1962 (Box 2)
  - Graduate and Professional Schools, 1958-1962 (Box 2)
  - Visiting Experts, 1958-1962 (Box 2)
    The reports and recommendations in this file come from experts from Harvard, Rice, the University of Pennsylvania, the University of Illinois, and the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. The material focuses on the departments of Economics, History, Physics, Classical Studies, English, and the Graduate School of Arts of and Sciences.
  - Progress Reports, 1958-1962 (Box 2)
- Reference Materials, 1958-1962 (Box 2)
  - Administrative Organization, 1958-1962 (Box 2)
  - Admissions and Enrollment, 1958-1962 (Box 2)
  - Charts and Projections, 1958-1962 (Box 2)
    Includes charts graphs, and projections dealing with academics, dormitories, and faculty appointments. Much of the material in this file deals with Duke in comparison to other schools.
  - Curriculum, 1958-1962 (Box 2)
  - Departments and Classifications, 1958 (Box 2)
    Arranged by classification, includes memos and reports that deal with the systematic approach that the Committee was to use in planning. The classifications are New Areas and Enterprises, Space Requirements and Needs, Strengthening What We Have, and Administration of Personnel.
  - Facilities, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Faculty Salaries, 1958-1959 (Box 2)
  - Duke University, School of Medicine Hospital Administration Program, 1958 and 1960 (Box 2)
  - Duke University Office of Institutional Advancement, 1962 (Box 2)
  - News Clipping, Durham Morning Herald, June 14, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Progress Reports, 1958-1962 (Box 2)
  - Visits of School and Colleges, 1958-1962 (Box 2)
    Includes information on other colleges and schools visited by Duke professors and staff. Schools include Harvard, Princeton, Swarthmore, Rice, Vanderbilt, Brown, Columbia, Yale, Tulane, Columbia and Wesleyan Universities, the Carnegie Institute of Technology, the University of Rochester, Union Theological Institute, Perkins School of Theology, the Hartford Seminary Foundation, Boston University School of Theology, Andover Newton Theological Institute, and Austin Presbyterian Theological Seminary. The information in this file deals with many aspects of college governance, academics, student life, and planning. It also includes a pamphlet entitled, Long Range Planning for Colleges and Universities, by Arnold F. Emich, 1958.
- Subcommittees and Committees, 1958-1962 (Box 3)
  - Subcommittee on the Undergraduate Colleges, 1958-1962 (Box 3)
    - Administrative Materials, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
      - Minutes, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
      - Final Report of the Subcommittee on the Undergraduate College, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
      - Reports, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
      - Recommendations, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1958-1960 (Box 3)
    - Reference Materials, 1958-1960 (Box 3)
      - Academic Averages, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
      - Academic Courses, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
      - Application Materials, 1960 (Box 3)
      - Athletics, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
      - Extracurricular Activities, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
        Contains lists of student organizations at the University.
      - General Subject Files, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
      - News Clippings, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
      - Placement Testing, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
      - Religious Life, 1958 (Box 3)
      - William H. Rice Institute/University, 1960 (Box 3)
      - Traffic Commission, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
      - Trinity College and the School of Engineering (Box 3)
      - West Campus Dormitories, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
      - Women's College, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
  - Committee on Professional and Graduate School, 1958-1962 (Box 3)
    - Organizational Materials, 1958-1962 (Box 3)
    - Report of the Sub-Committee on Matters Related to the Graduate School, undated (Box 3)
  - Committee on Faculty and Staff Improvement, 1960-1961 (Box 3)
Related Material
University Planning Committee Records, 1962-1964, 1971-1973.
University Archives, Duke University.
University Planning and Policy Advisory Committee Records, 1964-1969.
University Archives, Duke University.